Okay, so on this video we're going to
discuss the cost baseline.
So remember, there are four baselines.
You have the scope baseline, schedule
baseline, and the cost baseline.
And then the three of these put together
make up the performance
measurement baseline.
And each of these baselines then are a
component of the project management plan.
So in this video then we're going to be
talking about the cost baseline.
Now the cost baseline is the approved
version of the cost.
the approved version of the budget.
So this is the budget,
right, or the portion of the
budget that does not
include management reserves.
So this is the budget that the project
manager is responsible for.
It includes contingency reserves,
right?
So it's all of the planned costs on the
project plus a contingency reserve,
but it doesn't include the management
reserves.
So this is what you would call, if you
like, your project manager's budget.
Now, the budget also, whenever you're
coming up with a budget, you don't just
come up with one final budget at the end
of the project, right?
You have various performance levels
throughout the project.
So your cost baseline then is your time
phased budget throughout the project.
And your baseline budget is also known as
the budget at completion.
And we have a separate video on these,
right, separate videos on end value.
That's where we introduce this term,
budget at completion.
So BAC is budget at completion.
There's also another
term we'll be discussing
which is the EAC estimate at completion.
So anyway, we'll talk about that in just a
little while.
But the cost baseline is
your time phased budget,
not just one final budget
at the end of the project.
And it's usually shown as an S curve like
this.
It's usually shown as an S curve.
All right, so let's explain this then.
So on the y-axis, we have the cost,
right?
On the x-axis, we have timeline.
So we have beginning of the project all
the way until the end of the project,
right?
And then in between, right, these
increments here could either represent
phases or it could represent timeline,
like an actual time, days, weeks,
months, that kind of thing, years.
So that's why I've purposely left this
blank, right?
Because, you know, this could have,
you know, several meanings.
Like I said, each one of these could be a
phase on a project.
And here we're talking about predictive
projects, right?
We're specifically talking about
predictive projects here.
So you have beginning of the project,
end of the project.
And then on the y-axis,
you have the cost, and these
could be going in, you
know, in any increments.
Now, this curved line here, or the
S-curve, right, in the dark-colored line
here, this is your rate of
expenditure, or your planned
rate of, of expenditure
throughout your project, right?
So this is what is your cost baseline for
your project.
So at the beginning
of a project, your rate
of expenditure is not
going to be really high.
You don't have too many people on your
project, right?
You're just doing some initial planning
work.
You're not going to be using too many raw
materials or anything like that.
So your rate expenditure is going to be,
it's not going to be very high.
Now, as time progressed through the
project team members are rolling onto your
project right you're ordering raw
materials machine supplies you need all of
these to do your project your rate of
expenditure is going to increase right and
that as you're going towards the end of
the project the work has been completed
right some team members can roll off the
project right plus you're not using as
many raw materials raw materials are done
supplies we don't need as many supplies we
don't need as much
equipment, so the rate of
expenditure is going to flatten out again.
And so that's why we have this,
you know, so-called S-curve.
So this dark line here is our planned
expenditure.
And this is our BAC, so at the end,
so this is the end of the project,
that is our budget at completion.
That's known as our budget at completion.
And so our cost baseline is our time phase
budget at various
points along the project.
right and then what this red line here is
showing this is our actual expenditure
right so at this point in time say we're
down here we're at this point in on the
project so this has been our actual
expenditure so far and then the difference
is showing how much over budget or under
budget we might be at this point in time
right so right now at this you know if
we're looking at this particular say
snapshot point in time this is how much we
should have spent this is our planned cost
this is how much we actually spent that's
our actual cost and so then the difference
between the two will show us how much
we're over budget right now right and then
at this point in time like let's say we're
right here at this point in time right so
this is what our actual expenditure has
been so far so again the difference will
be how much over budget we are at this
point in time and then based on this right
notice this arrow here we can extrapolate
right we can you know use some kind of
extrapolation to determine, well,
how much over budget do you think we might
end up being by the end of the project,
right?
EAC refers to a term called estimate at
completion.
An estimate at completion is your
forecasted budget.
And we'll talk about that on a separate
video.
So that's known as your forecasted budget.
That's your estimate at completion.
So this line then here is basically your
cost baseline.
Remember the cost baseline then is your
time-phased budget, right?
That includes contingency reserves,
but not management reserves.
So this is what the project manager is
responsible for, right?
Now, some additional terms, or a couple of
additional terms I just want to mention
just in case they come up on the exam,
right?
A couple of cost considerations.
Financing.
Right, so financing user comes from
outside of the organization, right?
You know, bank loans as a simple example.
Now interest on the bank loan then can be
a cost consideration for your project.
So if you are, if your organization is
taken a loan specifically to finance your
project, then the interest on that loan
will be a direct cost to your project.
But if the organization is just taken a
loan to finance many activities,
and one of those activities
is your project, right,
then that might be
considered a an indirect cost.
It's still a cost consideration for your
project.
And then this other term lifecycle
costing.
Life cycle costing refers to the full life
of the product or the service.
It's not just the cost of installation or
implementation, right?
It's also looking at the entire life,
right?
Maintenance and, you know, upgrades and so
and so forth.
So as a very simple example, when you're
purchasing a car, you may have a few cars
in mind, right, a few options here and
there.
Well, you're not just looking at the
bottom line, what the final dollar amount
is for me to purchase
this car, you know, bring
it out of the showroom
into my house, right?
You're not just looking at the bottom line
just at final price.
You're also going to consider,
you know, things like fuel efficiency,
maintenance expenses, and, you know,
and other things.
So granted, you don't necessarily do a
three-year or five-year projection,
right, about how much,
you know, your car is going
to cost over, you know,
over a period of time.
But for life cycle costing, you do,
right?
You do a full projection, right?
So you look at, say, you know,
obviously the cost of installation,
cost of implementation, how long are we
going to keep this product?
What's a salvage cost?
What's the depreciation expenses,
right, then how much does it cost to
maintain an upgrade right before we
finally get rid of it?
So what is the actual full life of this
product going to cost us?
So that is what is referred to as life
cycle costing.
Okay.
So these are just a couple of additional
side terms that you need to be aware of.